Guide to the Indivisible: Stories of American Community photographs and project records, 1988-2002 and undated
Indivisible: Stories of American Community photographs and project records 1988-2002 and undated
Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies.
14.2 Linear Feet Approx. 7250 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
The Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University was established for the study of the documentary process.
The records of the documentary project Indivisible: Stories of American Community span the dates 1988-2002. Through documentary photographs and oral histories, project records, videos, and other materials, the collection documents the social conditions in twelve American communities as well as the history of the project, which explored civil activism, struggle, and change in the following locations: the North Pacific Coast of Alaska; Ithaca, N.Y.; San Francisco, California; Navajo Nation, Arizona and New Mexico; Eau Claire, South Carolina; Delray Beach, Florida; Western North Carolina; Stony Brook, N.Y.; San Juan, Texas; Chicago, Illinois; Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; and the Yaak Valley, Montana. The photographers are Dawoud Bey, Bill Burke, Debbie Fleming Caffery, Lucy Capehart, Lynn Davis, Terry Evans, Lauren Greenfield, Joan Liftin, Reagan Louie, Danny Lyon, Sylvia Plachy, and Eli Reed. The project was sponsored by the Center for Documentary Studies of Duke University and the Center for Creative Photography at the University of Arizona, and co-directed by Tom Rankin and Trudi Stack. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted. Images and recorded interviews may be used for non-commercial, public service, or educational purposes. All other requests to copy, reprint, or republish recorded interviews or printed materials must be made in writing to the Center for Documentary Studies. Researchers who wish to use an interview that does not have a release agreement must read and sign a Research Agreement for Restricted Materials. All quotes must be taken directly from the recorded interviews, not the printed transcripts or logs.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Also, some of the materials in this collection are not immediately accessible, because they require further processing before use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Indivisible: Stories of American Community photographs and project records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 2002,2006, 2008, and 2011.
Biographical Note
The Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University was established for the study of the documentary process. Indivisible: Stories of American Community was a national documentary project which took place primarily during 1999-2001, and was sponsored by the Center for Documentary Studies in partnership with the Center for Creative Photography at the University of Arizona. The project captured the experiences of individuals participating in grassroots community organizations and activism in twelve American communities at the end of the 20th century.
Collection Overview
The records of the documentary project Indivisible: Stories of American Community span the dates 1988-2002, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1999 to 2002, the primary timeframe for the project. Through documentary photographs and oral histories, project records, videos, and other materials, the collection documents the social conditions in twelve American communities as well as the history of the project, which explored civil activism, struggle, and change in the following locations: the North Pacific Coast of Alaska; Ithaca, N.Y.; San Francisco, California; Navajo Nation, Arizona and New Mexico; Eau Claire, South Carolina; Delray Beach, Florida; Western North Carolina; Stony Brook, N.Y.; San Juan, Texas; Chicago, Illinois; Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; and the Yaak Valley, Montana. Each project is fully described in its entry in this collection guide. The project co-directors were Tom Rankin of the Center for Documentary Studies and Trudy Wilner Stack of the Center for Creative Photography. The project was also supported by the Pew Charitable Trusts, the NEA, and other agencies.
The photographs in this collection, most of formed part of a traveling exhibit, were taken chiefly during 1999 by twelve well-known documentary and landscape photographers working in partnership with project oral history interviewers. The photographers are Dawoud Bey, Bill Burke, Debbie Fleming Caffery, Lucy Capehart, Lynn Davis, Terry Evans, Lauren Greenfield, Joan Liftin, Reagan Louie, Danny Lyon, Sylvia Plachy, and Eli Reed. Their images capture the experiences of individuals participating in grassroots initiatives addressing American social issues such as housing, immigration (in particular, Haitians in Florida), the natural environment, race relations, youth empowerment, and economic and cultural development, and others.
Also preserved in this collection are detailed oral histories recorded in each community, with audio recordings and transcriptions; information on the traveling exhibit; and materials on other project outcomes, including a hardbound large-format book of the images, a postcard exhibit, a guide for educators, booklets and other publications on community organizing, and radio and television programs. Other files document the establishment of research archives based on the documentary project's output, at Duke, in Arizona, and in each of the twelve communities.
The collection is arranged into two series: Project Files and Photographs. The first houses the interview records, including digital and analog cassette tapes of oral histories, as well as tape lists, logs, and transcripts in both paper and digital formats, and the project files described above. The second series houses the photographic prints, most of which were part of the traveling exhibition and the book. Additional supporting materials found in the Project Files Series include postcards and videocassette tapes from exhibits; a CD-ROM of the 2001 website; field notes in paper and digital format; and other office files generated by the project and its staff, including Tom Rankin, one of the project co-directors. There are also slides of the and biographies of the photographers. Three hundred thirty-nine of the electronic transcripts have been migrated to the electronic records server. A disk directories log and use copies exist. Please contact Research Services staff before coming to use this collection.
Acquired as part of the Archives for Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Bey, Dawoud, 1953-
Burke, Bill, 1943-
Caffery, Debbie Fleming
Capehart, Lucy
Davis, Lynn, 1944-
Evans, Terry
Greenfield, Lauren
Liftin, Joan, 1935-
Louie, Reagan
Lyon, Danny
Plachy, Sylvia
Reed, Eli
Rankin, Tom
Stack, Trudi Wilner
Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies
University of Arizona. Center for Creative Photography
Documentary photography -- United States
Community life -- United States -- Pictorial works
Oral history -- United States
Social problems -- United States -- History -- 20th century
Community organization -- United States
Community development -- United States
Voluntarism -- United States
Chicago (Ill.)--Social conditions -- 1980-
Delray Beach (Fla.)--Social conditions -- 1980-
Eau Claire (S.C.)--Social conditions -- 1980-
Ithaca (N.Y.)--Social conditions -- 1980-
Navajo Nation, Arizona, New Mexico & Utah -- Social conditions -- 1980-
North Carolina, Western -- Social conditions -- 1980-
Pacific Coast (Alaska)--Social conditions -- 1980-
Philadelphia (Penna.)--Social conditions -- 1980-
San Francisco (Calif.)--Social conditions -- 1980-
San Juan (Tex.)--Social conditions -- 1980-
Stony Brook (N.Y.)--Social conditions -- 1980-
Yaak Valley (Mont.)--Social conditions -- 1980-
United States -- Social conditions -- 1980-
Audiocassettes
CD-ROMs
Machine-readable records
Oral histories
Photographs
Slides
Videocassettes
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Contents of Collection
- Project Files Series, 1988-2002 and undated, (27 boxes)
  Contains a variety of project records: administrative files, tape logs and oral history transcripts, publicity materials, photographer and interviewer biographies, project documentation in the form of slides, and other supporting materials documenting the scope and unfolding of the project and its associated book and traveling exhibit. THere are also audio and video recordings related to interviews and other project-related work.
  Images and recorded interviews may be used for non-commercial, public service, or educational purposes. All other requests to copy, reprint, or republish recorded interviews or printed materials must be made in writing to the Center for Documentary Studies. Researchers who wish to use an interview that does not have a release agreement must read and sign a Research Agreement for Restricted Materials. All quotes must be taken directly from the recorded interviews, not the printed transcripts or logs.
  [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
  - Logs (Box 1)
  - Tape lists
  - Tape lists (Box 2)
  - Postcards
  - Tape lists and transcripts for Delray Beach, Village of Arts and Humanities, Handmade in America, and Proyecto Azteca (Box 3)
  - Tape lists (Box 4)
  - Tape lists and transcripts for Alaska Fishing Communities, and folders of project information for Eau Claire, Handmade in America, Proyecto Azteca, Southwest Youth Collaborative, Village of Arts and Humanities, and Yaak Valley (Box 5)
  - Fact-checking and captions files
  - Tom Rankin files
  - Check-list
  - Postcard captions
  - Book bios
  - Possible volunteers
  - Site-specific concerns
  - Library materials
  - Getting started
  - CHALK (Calif.) transcripts (Box 6)
  - Doula transcripts
  - Dine Bi Iina transcripts (Navajo Nation)
  - Fact checking files
  - Possible community activist sites
  - Give Back: files on process of finding local archives sites after each project
  - Pew Charitable Trust files (Box 7)
  - Radio project/program for Village of Arts and Humanities
  - Project background
  - Guides for educators
  - Tom Rankin files
  - Publicity files (correspondence, resumes, radio programs, proposals, press releases)
  - Give Back (files on finding local archive sites after each project) (Box 8)
  - Video: Talking Cloths: Making Art and Making Community: Village of Arts and Humanity (VHS), 2002
  - Computer Discs: Full Set Community Discs for Main Archive
  - Tape logs and transcripts for Alaska Fishing Communities (Box 9)
  - Community archives files (correspondence, offer letters)
  - Project feedback (Box 10)
  - Zip disk with scanned images of headshots (content of slides?)
  - Press coverage files
  - Tape logs and transcripts for Delray Beach, Handmade in America, Yaak Valley, Eau Claire, Village of Arts and Humanities, and Dine Bi Iina (Navajo Nation)
  - Tape logs and transcripts (Box 11)
  - Publicity files
  - NEA grant file and other grant information (Box 12)
  - Center for Creative Photography file
  - Conferences
  - Contracts and other exhibit files
  - Forms and facts
  - Pew Charitable Trusts files
  - Village of Arts and Humanities project files (captions, articles)
  - Southwest Youth Collaborative (Box 13)
  - Yaak Valley Forest Council
  - Daniel Rothenberg
  - Jeff Whetstone
  - Dan Collison
  - Slides: 35mm color images taken during project; images include portraits of community individuals, of photographers, and other scenes, (approx. 234 items) (Box 14)
  - Documentary photographer and interviewer biographies and other information such as publicity, photographers' past project, and some correspondence
  - Slides: 35mm color images arranged by photographer, and exhibit installation shots, (approx. 200 slides) (Box 14-A)
  - Photographer biographies (cont.) (Box 15)
  - Doula project transcripts
  - Comprehensive files on Doula, Eau Claire, and Navajo projects (field notes, articles, captions, supporting materials for projects)
  - Comprehensive files on Alternatives Credit Union, Handmade in America, Delray Beach, Citizens on Patrol, and CHALK projects (field notes, articles, captions, supporting materials for projects) (Box 16)
  - Comprehensive files on Alaska Fishing Communities and Proyecto Azteca projects (field notes, articles, captions, supporting materials for projects) (Box 17)
  - CDs of contemporary popular Hispanic music (unopened)
  - Proyecto Azteca (NM) transcripts
  - Press packet for Indivisible
  - Tape logs (no transcripts) for all project locations (Box 18)
  - Proyecto Azteca transcripts
  - Outreach, exhibit files
  - Postcard exhibit
  - Launch money
  - Travel
  - VIP lists (invitees)
  - Location interviews (Box 19)
  - Location interviews (Box 20)
  - Location interviews (Box 21)
  - Location interviews (Box 23)
    [Original audio and video materials are closed to use. Technical Services needs to reformat for use copies of audio and digital materials materials before contents can be accessed. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
  - Transcripts
  - Transcripts (Box 24)
  - Field notes
  - Location interview recordings (Box 25)
  - Location interview recordings (Box 26)
  - VHS Videos
    - "Indivisible Exhibit [TV program?], KVOA, 9/06/1999" (Box 26)
    - "Indivisible Chicago VNR [Video News Report?] with R. Suarez and all B-Roll and photographs, 9/20/00"
    - "Indivisible PSA [Public Service Announcement?] 9/20/2000"
    - "Exhibit 12/14/2001, UNC TV" [running time about 30 minutes?]
- Photographs Series, 1999-2002, (20 boxes)
  Prints in various sizes, chiefly in black and white, taken by documentary photographers in project locations: Alaska, Arizona, California, Florida, Illinois, Montana, New Mexico, New York, and Wisconsin. All captions and contextual notes have been taken from the original source. Unless otherwise noted, images were also published in the volume, Indivisible: Stories of American Community, and formed the traveling exhibit by the same name. Each print is prefaced by a unique identification number assigned by the photographers. Arranged in subseries alphabetically by photographer's last name.
  - Dawoud Bey (United States, b. 1953)
    Seventeen black and white gelatin silver prints of community organizations and individuals in Chicago, Illinois, with the chief focus on members of the Southwest Youth Collaborative, an effort on the part of faith-based institutions, social service centers, recreational centers, and neighborhood organizations to empower youth and their community in South Chicago neighborhoods.
    - Danyale, West Englewood Youth and Teen Center, 1999, (L2000:040:001a-b); (two prints) (Box 37)
    - Aron Hanson, Youth Organizer, Community Justice Initiative, 1999, (L2000:040:002a-b, L2000:040:003, L2000:040:004, L2000:040:005); (5 prints) (Box 37)
    - Trenton, Greater Lawn Community Youth Network, 1999, (L2000:040:006) (Box 37)
    - Adriana Bartow, Director, Greater Lawn Community Youth Network, 1999, (L2000:040:007) (Box 37)
    - Darrin, West Englewood Youth and Teen Center, 1999, (L2000:040:008) (Box 37)
    - Geoff Banks, Youth Organizer, Community Justice Initiative, 1999, (L2000:040:009) (Box 37)
    - Alma Montes, Staff, Greater Lawn Community Youth Network, 1999, (L2000:040:010) (Box 37)
    - Janette Maldonado, Peer Mentor, Community Justice Initiative, 1999, (L2000:040:011a-b); (2 prints) (Box 37)
    - Dowua, Greater Lawn Community Youth Network, 1999, (L2000:040:012) (Box 37)
    - Keith Hopkins, Youth Coordinator of Reach Out and Touch, West Englewood Youth and Teen Center, 1999, (L2000:040:013) (Box 37)
    - Sherry Brown, Peer Mentor, West Englewood Youth and Teen Center, 1999, (L2000:040:014) (Box 37)
  - Bill Burke (United States, b. 1943)
    Thirty-one 8x10 and 16x20 black-and-white gelatin silver prints of individuals involved with the Alternatives Credit Union in Ithaca, N.Y. The Credit Union's policies and programs are focused on supporting community-based economic development through access to loans, mortgages, and other financial services for high-risk or low income clients.
    - Camila Vargas, 1999, (L2000:038:001) (Box 44)
    - Tahila Mintz, 1999, (L2000:038:002) (Box 44)
    - Kenneth Broadwell, 1999, (L2000:038:003) (Box 44)
    - Black Peter Donovan, 1999, (L2000:038:004) (Box 44)
    - Paul Glover, 1999, (L2000:038:005) (Box 44)
    - Joseph Wetmore, 1999, (L2000:038:006) (Box 44)
    - Dennis Montgomery, 1999, (L2000:038:007) (Box 44)
    - Scott Engelhart, 1999, (L2000:038:008) (Box 42)
    - Bill Myers, 1999, (L2000:038:009) (Box 42)
    - Paul Carubia, 1999, (L2000:038:010) (Box 42)
    - Joey Kilmer, 1999, (L2000:038:018) (Box 42)
      Not in traveling exhibition.
    - Jeff Furman, 1999, (L2000:038:019) (Box 42)
    - Tim Brown, 1999, (L2000:038:020) (Box 42)
    - Karen Nguyen, 1999, (L2000:038:011) (Box 43)
    - Laberta McGruder, 1999, (L2000:038:012) (Box 43)
    - Amber Boyd, 1999, (L2000:038:013) (Box 43)
    - Leslie Muhlhahn, 1999, (L2000:038:014) (Box 43)
    - Lekeesa Jones, 1999, (L2000:038:015) (Box 43)
      Not in book or traveling exhibition.
    - Jenny Ross, 1999, (L2000:038:016) (Box 43)
      Not in book.
    - Emme Edmunds, 1999, (L2000:038:017) (Box 43)
    - Bathroom of Don Ruff and Barbara Brazill's owner-built, Alternatives-financed home, 1999, (L2000:038:021) (Box 15)
    - Metalsmith and blacksmith Durand Van Doren, owns Durand's Forge and is an Alternatives business member, 1999, (L2000:038:022) (Box 15)
    - Alternatives member Steven E. Valloney and Charlotte Rosen at the Sunrise Yoga Center, which Valloney owns, 1999, (L2000:038:023) (Box 15)
    - Justin Armstrong, a Cayuga Wooden Boatworks employee, 1999, (L2000:038:024) (Box 15)
    - Home of Zan Gerrity and Inge Alexander outside Ithaca in Slaterville Springs, New York, 1999, (L2000:038:025) (Box 15)
    - Sisay Sisouphone, proprietor of Sticky Rice restaurant and catering service, is a beneficiary of the Community Enterprise Opportunities program at Alternatives, 1999, (L2000:038:026) (Box 15)
    - Rob Root, Dave Engasser, and Matt Lee of Cascadilla Tree Care, an Alternatives business member, 1999, (L2000:038:027) (Box 15)
    - Jonathan Kline, Alternatives member and owner of Black Ash Baskets, 1999, (L2000:038:028) (Box 15)
    - Raina White at RIBS [Recycle Ithaca's Bicycles], a community bicycle repair shop that is a business member of the credit union, 1999, (L2000:038:029) (Box 15)
    - Rick Dobson, owner of Danby Motors, an Alternatives business member, 1999, (L2000:038:030) (Box 15)
    - Alternatives-financed Long Point Winery building under construction, 1999, (L2000:038:031) (Box 15)
  - Debbie Fleming Caffery (United States, b. 1948)
    Twenty-one 20x24" black-and-white gelatin silver prints of communities and individuals in the western North Carolina mountains involved with "Handmade in America," a cooperative of craftsmen and craftswomen designed to promote self-suffiency and locally-based economic development.
    - Madison County Courthouse, Marshall, North Carolina, July 4, 1999, (L2000:056:001) (Box 33)
    - Woodrow Lail, Marshall, North Carolina, in Penland's Store, 1999, (L2000:056:002) (Box 33)
    - Bakersville Baptist Church, 1999, (L2000:056:003) (Box 33)
    - Penlands', Marshall, NC, 1999, (L2000:056:004) (Box 33)
    - Police Chief Denny Goforth and Justin Jones, Rock Cafe, Marshall, North Carolina, 1999, (L2000:056:005) (Box 33)
    - Stella Riddles' 14 four-leaf clovers, 1999, (L2000:056:006) (Box 33)
    - Bakersville Barber and Gun shop, Bakersville, NC, 1999, (L2000:056:007) (Box 33)
    - True Love, Marshall, North Carolina, 1999, (L2000:056:008) (Box 33)
    - Davitus Gosnell, July 4, 1999, (L2000:056:009) (Box 33)
    - "The Depot," 1999, (L2000:056:010) (Box 33)
    - Rodeo clown Randy Wilson, Marshall, North Carolina, 1999, (L2000:056:011) (Box 33)
    - Love Gunther, Gunther Town, NC, 1999, (L2000:056:012) (Box 33)
    - Ryan, 1999, (L2000:056:013) (Box 33)
    - Davitus, July 4, 1999, (L2000:056:014) (Box 33)
    - Prayer and Preparation, Marshall, NC, July 4, 1999, (L2000:056:015) (Box 33)
    - Amerady Cantrell's hummingbird beans, Shelton Laurel, North Carolina, 1999, (L2000:056:016) (Box 33)
    - The dreaded door, Marshall, North Carolina, 1999, (L2000:056:017) (Box 33)
    - Stacy Lee Wilson, volunteer fireman, Marshall, North Carolina, 1999, (L2000:056:018) (Box 33)
    - Carolina For Sale, Spruce Pine, North Carolina, 1999, (L2000:056:019) (Box 33)
    - Penland's store, Marshall, North Carolina, 1999, (L2000:056:020) (Box 33)
    - Praying before bull riding, North Carolina, 1999, (L2000:056:021) (Box 33)
  - Lucy Capehart (United States, b. 1952)
    Sixteen chromogenic prints of Native American individuals and their historic-breed animals, in their Navajo Nation communities in New Mexico and Arizona.
    - Tony Vanderveer at home, near Haystack Mountain, New Mexico, 1999, (L2000:059:001) (Box 29)
    - Interior, Sarah Natani's hogan with rugs woven by Sarah, Table Mesa near Shiprock, New Mexico, 1999, (L2000:059:002) (Box 29)
    - Sarah Natani in her sheep corral, Table Mesa near Shiprock, New Mexico, 1999, (L2000:059:003) (Box 29)
    - Sheep near Polacca, Arizona, 1999, (L2000:059:004) (Box 29)
    - Sarah Natani's sheep heading out to pasture, Table Mesa near Shiprock, New Mexico, 1999, (L2000:059:005) (Box 29)
    - Three Churro rams, Navajo Sheep Project's herd, Bloomfield, New Mexico, 1999, (L2000:059:006) (Box 29)
    - Mary Oskie in front of her log cabin near Ganado, Arizona, 1999, (L2000:059:007) (Box 29)
    - Untitled, [spinning wool into yarn] 1999, (L2000:059:008) (Box 29)
    - Marlene Benally and Al Largo, Begay Ranch kitchen, Jeddito Island, Navajo Nation, Arizona, 1999, (L2000:059:009) (Box 29)
    - Mountain sheep pictograph near Bluff, Utah, 1999, (L2000:059:010) (Box 29)
    - Mutton case, in a traditional Navajo meat store, Farmington, New Mexico, 1999, (L2000:059:011) (Box 29)
    - Lena Benally, a member of Diné bí' íína's board of directors, and her grandson, Donnie, Begay Ranch, Jeddito Island, Navajo Nation, Arizona, 1999, (L2000:059:012) (Box 29)
    - Sarah Natani holding a newborn lamb, Table Mesa, near Shiprock, New Mexico, 1999, (L2000:059:013) (Box 29)
    - Sheep and bucket near Polacca, Arizona, 1999, (L2000:059:014) (Box 29)
    - Interior, Begay Ranch, Jeddito Island, Navajo Nation, Arizona, 1999, (L2000:059:015) (Box 29)
    - Untitled [five dogs], 1999, (L2000:059:016) (Box 29)
  - Lynn Davis (United States, b. 1944)
    Twenty-one 11x14" toned black and white silver gelatin prints of Alaskan landscapes and fishing communities, documenting change and struggle in the community members' lives.
    - Bob Storrs and his House, Unalaska, Aleutians, 1999, (L2000:008:001 a-c); (3 prints) (Box 37)
    - Landscape of Unalaska; Walter Tellman; Walter and Brenda Tellman in Their Boat, Aleutians, 1999, (L2000:008:002 a-c); (3 prints) (Box 37)
    - Volcano from Eric's Boat, Sitka, Alaska, 1999, (L2000:008:003) (Box 37)
    - Little Priest Rock, Sitka, 1999, (L2000:008:004) (Box 37)